[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event for the 2024 release Wave 1 my
name is Kenny pidan and I'm Yan M
Peterson and together we work on the AL
runtime and the database in this session
we're going to talk about the data stack
and the runtime and then we have a few
other sessions on the web service stack
and Reporting
changes so let's talk
data in this release wave we added some
new capabilities to the number sequence
object and we also tuned the existing
methods so first of all next current
exist methods are up to 32% faster and
we also introduced these two new methods
one the ability to restart a number
sequence and two the the ability to get
multiple numbers without having to call
SQL every single time so the way they
work is for restart before this you
would have to like drop the sequence
create a new one with a new restart
method you can simply as the code
example here States you can restart to a
particular uh number and then you start
picking numbers from
there similarly range start is a way for
you to get an interval of an interval of
numbers you can of course achieve this
with a number sequence if you if you
increment by say 10 you would get 10
numbers each time but in this case you
can also simply say I would like a range
of something and that will then for the
increment you have chosen give you that
range without having to call the
database yeah so you're basically saving
a datab base call for every time you
need a number so if if you have a range
of 100 numbers it's not one call
compared to 100
yes so that's it for number sequences
actually something a lot of people start
noticing that this can speed up quite
significant uh the insert performance of
things compared to to Auto increments
yeah particularly also compared to this
where you lock the last record in order
to pick the highest number Etc which can
really hurt your performance with with
locking scenarios
y all right now let's talk about another
problem we've had which is the time it
takes to clean up the change log entes
we have seen change log entry tables
growing to very large sizes to the point
where even setting up retention policies
would time out and deleting elements
from the change log entry would also
time out so we basically had to make
this faster to enable our customers to
get out of this
situation in order to do that we
optimize some internal workings but we
also needed to create a new method which
for now is mar for on premises because
it is a little bit of a double-edged
sort but let's talk about this new alter
key method that you might see if you're
coding with the on premise um keyword so
the alter key it disables
Keys during the current
transaction meaning that it is it's
almost the same as if you've dropped the
index and then you do all your deletes
and then you reenable it and it is
automatically reenable when the current
transaction ends that can either be due
to the transaction being canceled due to
an error in which case the transaction
is rolled back or unsuccessful
completion or add an explicit Al commit
so why aren't we just opening this up
always well it's not always a good idea
because the index needs to be rebuilt
again afterwards when it is re-enabled
so it is only viable when you need to
delete a lot of
data this has allowed us to speed up the
deletion of change log entries
significantly and hence allowing our
customers to clean up those tables
now small announcement we have
previously said that we would remove the
force order and loop join server
settings they are now and it was
announced in 23 it was a thing from the
past now it is
removed all right let's talk about the
runtime one of the things that if you
have been to any of our yens and I
session from the past actually from
directions a few years back we handed
out these sheets where you could vote on
features and this is on paper on paper
for gdpr then we could burn them know
yes and now uh now one of these ideas
actually made it to the product tool
tips on table Fields so with this
release wave as developer you can now
Define field tool tips once on the table
and any page uh that that use these
fields would just inherit the tool tips
you don't have to Define them on
multiple Pages can I add a comment there
now of course if you don't want the tool
tip that was defined on the table then
you can still override it on the control
just like you can with caption so think
about the same pattern as for captions
yes this gives some opportunities
advantages this is actually why we build
it in the first place now uh first of
all we can use it in co-pilot features
internally and later we might do this
same for queries and maybe in report
data set so you can Define things on the
table level and inherit it up but for
now that's science fiction not coming in
this release wave so the way to define a
tool tip on a table field is basically
just do it um and then um it will
inherit up we have also have our
friendly compiler team at code um code
actions in case you want to move tool
chip down from the page to the table and
I believe if if it's not there already
it will also be possible not only on the
actual page but on a project level or a
folder level yeah I'm afraid it didn't
make it for this release but um it will
go out with a later um compiler update
where for the individual file or
potentially even for the whole project
you'll do this got
it yeah yeah and actually with this tool
tips it gave us also a need to rethink
how we actually store texts in the
system because tool tips can be
relatively large and we don't really
want to store them together with the
objects um just like we do for captions
so behind the scenes so here you'll get
a small glimpse of what's Happening
behind the scenes we have added new
system tables to store these
translatable texts now you'll be
providing those through xliff files or
similar and um and then we will take
them and store them in particular tables
rather than in the normal metadata table
and Tool tip is the first usage of this
but we expect to expand this to also do
captions Etc because it allows us to
cach more efficiently and avoid
duplication of a number of these texts
so if you look inside the database in
version 24 you might see some new um
system tables both in the tenant
database and in the app database I'm not
going to go into details what they are
but now at least if you look and you
find these tables then these are the
tables being used to store the text
metadata in an efficient way and we
expect uh that this will allow us to
search more efficiently and generally
have a lower memory footprint
MH now another now let's switch gears to
something more ux related now in
previous releases you know you hopefully
know that we added the ability to add
navigation actions and fix it actions to
error info but we also know that there
are hundreds or thousands of usages of
test field in the product where you
check whether a value is blank or
similar and of course the best thing is
to actually go and code it completely
right with error info Etc but we thought
well how can we actually move this
forward without putting a lot of burden
on the application developers so we've
added new capabilities to test field so
that it can add link to add a navigation
link to the failing data so the data
that shouldn't be blank or the data that
should be a given value it will add this
navigation link if a number of consist
conditions are present that it needs to
be able to figure out what page to
navigate to using drill down page ID and
card page ID the user needs to have read
permission and it needs to be to a
different record and a different page
than you're currently at because you
don't want a second copy of what you
have already opened so yens just for me
to understand this this this means this
is the just the a runtime that would do
it for these four conditions we will add
uh we will add to this new actionable
era yes and if you take here in the
general ledger setup if you set up an
additional reporting currency then you
might see this error dialogue with
residual gains account is not being
valid for this particular
currency now the runtime will
automatically in this case add the show
currency card link which will take you
to the currency card for the Australian
dollars the AUD in this case and as you
can see then the residual gains account
is indeed blank for this value so
instead of you having to know how to
navigate using the normal navigation
structure to currencies we're now
offering that directly from the error
dialogue if the conditions for showing
it are fulfilled yeah and this requires
no coding on the app developers at all
so a certain percentage of the existing
test Fields will now have improved
usability very nice yens we also added
in case you need to handle errors we
haded and added a lot of new content to
our documentation for Developers for
error handling including failure model
modeling and a way to reason over errors
called robust coding practices so go
check that out if you work in a uh so
that you can create error messages that
well that you can degrade gracefully in
in certain cases so that users don't get
error messages and if they do there's
also guidance here of how to express
error uh errors in a language that users
understand and of course use the new
actionable error framework that was
introduced last
year all right now we want to talk also
or mention another thing which is
transparent for Al developers which is
that the server now runs on net 8
previous release we moved from Net
Framework to net core so version 23 was
running on net 6 but for this release we
have switched to net 8 which is a faster
and more efficient runtime and whenever
there are there is evolution in the net
stack then we benefit from it now this
should be transparent for all Al
developers you canot feel the difference
however you may feel a difference on
your automation scripts against the
server because with doet 8 we're moving
to Powers shell
so we know that there are number of
scripts out there and we know that you
may or may not be able to move directly
to pow shell 7 so we're also providing
basically a bridge from Powershell 5
into Powers shell 7 so you'll now have
two sets of dlls for the management
operations you will have the old admin
the sorry the old management folder
where we've Consolidated the assemblers
into one the nav management
dlll if you call that that will then
relay the calls to the new Powershell 7
dlls which are in the admin folder
meaning that you can still run
Powershell five Scripts
against uh the server but we highly
recommend to move to Powershell 7 and
will deprecate Parell five within the
next years yes exactly and so to
summarize on the next slide
there go ahead move to Powershell 7 we
do have a backward compatibility bridge
and which will call into the pow shell 7
command Leets it will be deprecated now
if you import the nav admin
tool um then it'll automatically pick
the right version it'll check are you
running Powershell 7 or are you running
Powershell 5 so in general your scripts
should still run if you have imported
the old assemblies directly rather than
through nav admin tool then you may have
to make minor changes cool that leaves
us to Goos for this session yeah and
some of the things to take away from
this is to go ahead and optimize your
number sequences you can refactor it to
use the new methods um when you have
restart scenarios or where you need to
draw ranges of
numbers you can start using tool tips on
table fields and get the benefit as we
expand on that
capability and as just mentioned
refactor to Powershell 7 scripts and for
error handling start really think about
using robust code practicing and failure
modeling start using actionable error
where it makes sense and uh adopt these
new error message guidelines so that
users have a better experience should
your code um make an
error that's it other language sorry
other uh launch event sessions that
might be relevant if you are in this one
um the first two here what's new in
Excel layouts and what's new in web
services
uh the kind of the package on the a
runtime there's also if you're
interested in web services uh learning
session on all integration scenarios
where we improved documentation for that
so if you're into web services you might
be interest in into Integrations and
therefore that session could be relevant
and of course if you are into the a
runtime you are likely also a developer
Al developer so the watch new in Visual
Studio code and Al development uh is a
session for you and also there's a new
what's new session on key improvements
in developer docks that you might also
want to check
out finally a few AKA links as always BC
Yammer is your Yammer is the place where
we discuss things internally if it's not
suitable for social media in in general
BC all is the the AKA link to uh to rule
them all uh BC ID is is where you uh
talk about new features that you might
want to add us to add to the product and
then for social media in X and Linkedin
we are active in on these platforms um
and finally office hours in case you
want to to attend live conversations
about things or if you want to to watch
recordings of U office hours in the past
the BC office hours AKA link is where
you go and with that yens and I would
like to say yeah thank you thank
you